<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet title="Creating a Text-Folding Updater for a new SAFARI IDE">
<intro>
<description>
The goal of this step is to create a service that supports the folding of hierarchical syntactic elements in text editors for the language.
As for most SAFARi services, the SAFARI wizard for text folding creates a skeleton class that contains the generic structure to support text
folding and this class must be tailored to the specifics of the language being defined.
<br/><br/>

This step must be performed after the grammar and parsing service have been defined,
but it can be performed in any order with respect to the generation of other IDE services.
<br/><br/>

</description>
</intro>

<item title="Create a folding updater">
<action pluginId="com.ibm.watson.safari.cheatsheets"
        class="com.ibm.watson.safari.cheatsheets.actions.NewFoldingUpdaterAction"/>
<description>

 The SAFARI wizard that does this is called “NewFoldingUpdater.”  To run this wizard, invoke<br/><br/>

"File" -> "New" -> "IDE Language Support" -> "Editor Services" -> "Source folding updater"<br/><br/>

As before, in the wizard assure that the names of the project and language are correct and, if desired,
edit the package and class name for the implementation. Hit "Finish" when done.
<br/><br/>

The NewFoldingUpdater wizard creates a safari.foldingUpdater package containing a FoldingUpdater class.
The wizard also adds a folding updater extension to the plugin.xml file for the language project and opens the FoldingUpdater class in an editor.
<br/><br/>

FoldingUpdater contains one main method, updateFoldingStructure(..).  This method obtains the current AST
and sends it a new FoldingVisitor, which is implemented in the FoldingUpdater and extends AbstractVisitor.
The visitor should contain a visit method for each AST node type for which folding is desired.
Each visit method should simply call AbstractVisitor.makeAnnotation(..) with its given node.
The method makeAnnotation makes an annotation that spans the text represented by the node,
and it is through the annotations that folding is enabled.
The language-specific customizations required for folding are simply to provide visit(..)
methods for the AST node types for which text is to be foldable.
These visit(..) methods should return true if folding should be allowed for nested units and false if not.
It may be necessary to add more complicated logic if more precise control of folding is desired, for example,
if you wish to enable folding of top-level blocks but not nested blocks.
<br/><br/>

Note:  The NewFoldingUpdater wizard requires the package and class names for the language AST node type.
The wizard currently assumes that the AST node type has the default name and is located in the default package.
If these assumptions are not valid, then incorrect names for this package and class will be entered into the generated FoldingUpdater class.
If that happens, the class should be edited to fill in the correct names.
<br/><br/>	

</description>
</item>


</cheatsheet>
