<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet title="Creating a Programming-Language Description for a new SAFARI IDE">
<intro>
<description>
This cheat sheet describes the process of creating a language descriptor
for a new SAFARI IDE.
This is the required first step in SAFARI-IDE creation.
<br/><br/>


<b>Notes:</b>
<br/><br/>

A SAFARI IDE must be created in a plugin project, and
each SAFARI IDE must be created in a distinct project.
If you don't have a distinct plugin project for your new IDE then
you may want to create one before continuing through this cheat sheet.
<br/><br/>

A note about plugin classes:  When you use the Eclipse New Project wizard to create a
new plugin project, the wizard creates a package with the name of the project.
In that package the wizard creates a plugin class with a name of the form "&lt;ProjectName&gt;Plugin.java."
The Safari New Programming Language wizard likewise creates a new package and plugin class,
but named based on the programming language rather than on the project.
If you use the default values in each wizard, you can end up with two plugin classes,
each in a different package.
<br/><br/>

There are two ways to avoid this.  One is just to give your project and language the same name.
The other is, during plugin-project creation, to override the default values and give your plugin
class and package a name that matches that of your language.
<br/><br/>


</description>
</intro>

<item title="Create a language description">
<action pluginId="com.ibm.watson.safari.cheatsheets"
        class="com.ibm.watson.safari.cheatsheets.actions.NewLanguageAction"/>
<description>
Invoke "File" -&gt; "New" -&gt; "IDE Language Support" -&gt; "Programming Language".
<br/><br/>

In the "Programming Language" wizard, you must provide information for the following required fields:<br/><br/>
    * Project:  Browse to or type-in the name of your language project<br/><br/>
    * Language:  Enter the name of the language (which for now must be the same as the name of the project).
    This is the canonical name for your language, by which it will be identified to various SAFARI services.
    Within SAFARI it is case-insensitive.<br/><br/>
    * Description:  The “description” field is for the entry of a user-readable, user-sensible description of the language.
    Enter whatever description you think is appropriate.<br/><br/>
    * Extensions:  The “extensions” field is for the entry of file-name extensions that may be used for source files in the language.
    Enter a non-empty, comma-separated list of extensions (omitting dots, and without spaces).
    The SAFARI services defined for your language will be available for files with these extensions.
<br/><br/><br/>

You may also provide information in the following optional fields:<br/><br/>
    * Synonyms:  This is a comma-separated list of alternative names for your language<br/><br/>
    * DerivedFrom:  The “derivedFrom” field should be the canonical name of the programming language,
    if any, from which the new language is derived.  The "derived from" language, if any, should be one
    for which there is already a SAFARI IDE.
    It is used within SAFARI for determining inheritance relationships when locating language services
    for a given language (for example, locating an appropriate editor if none is defined specifically for your language).
    If your language is derived from another SAFARI-supported language then this field should be filled in accordingly.
    If your language is not derived from another SAFARI-supported language then this field should be ignored.<br/><br/>
    * Icon:  This should be the project-relative pathname of an icon that can be used in graphical interfaces
    to mark files in your language.<br/><br/>
    * URL:  This is intended for the URL of a web page that contains information about your language.<br/><br/>
    * Validator:  The “validator” field can be given the fully-qualified name of a class that can determine
    whether a given input file actually contains text in the given programming language.
    This class must extend the LanguageValidator class.
<br/><br/><br/>

Hit “Finish” when you are done editing the various fields in the wizard.
A SAFARI language description extension will be created using the above information and added to the project’s plugin.xml file.
This step also updates the projects Plugin class (to extend SAFARIPluginBase, among other modifications),
or it will create a Plugin class if one does not exist.
<br/><br/>

(In earlier versions of SAFARI, this wizard also generates a "preferences" package and some preferences-related classes.
In later versions this feature will probably be eliminated as a separate wizard has been provided for generating a preferences
service and preference pages.)
<br/>


</description>
</item>



</cheatsheet>
