<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet title="Creating a New SAFARI Programming Language using JikesPG">
<intro>
<description>
This cheat sheet describes the basic process for creating a new SAFARI-based
IDE for a specific programming language.
It is assumed here that the language parser is generated using JikesPG (although this
is not a requirement for SAFARI in general, and many of the comments given here
will apply to languages with parsers based on other technologies).
<br/><br/>

SAFARI uses extensions to Eclipse to provide language-specific IDE capabilities
such as text editing, token coloring, outlining, source folding, hyperlink detection,
and project building.
These extensions are implemented by SAFARI-provided or -generated classes that
reqiure some customization by the user, usually relatively minor.
The goal is to enable SAFARI users to focus on the language-dependent aspects
of IDE capabilities that are of specific interest to them and to allow users
to ignore, insofar as possible, the generic infrastructure hacking that
is necessary to realize these capabilities in Eclipse.
<br/><br/>

<b>Notes:</b>
<br/><br/>

This cheat sheet describes a straight-line process that covers the creation
of several language services.  Although the language description and parser
are necessary for the implementation and execution of later services, the later
services may actually be addressed in any order and may be skipped if not of
interest.
<br/><br/>

The new IDE must be created in an existing plugin project.
Thus, you may want to create a new, language-specific plugin
project before continuing through this cheat sheet.
Each SAFARI IDE has to be defined in a distinct project.
<br/><br/>

A note about plugin classes:  When you use the Eclipse New Project wizard to create a
new plugin project, the wizard creates a package with the name of the project.
In that package the wizard creates a plugin class with a name of the form "&lt;ProjectName&gt;Plugin.java."
The Safari New Programming Language wizard likewise creates a new package and plugin class,
but named based on the programming language rather than on the project.
If you use the default values in each wizard, you can end up with two plugin classes,
each in a different package.
There are two ways to avoid this.  One is just to give your project and language the same name.
The other is, during plugin-project creation, to override the default values and give your plugin
class and package a name that matches that of your language.
<br/><br/>


</description>
</intro>

<item title="Create a language description">
<action pluginId="org.eclipse.imp.cheatsheets"
        class="org.eclipse.imp.cheatsheets.actions.NewLanguageAction"/>
<description>
Invoke "File" -&gt; "New" -&gt; "IDE Language Support" -&gt; "Programming Language".
<br/><br/>

Enter (or browse to) the project in which you want to create your language.
Fill out the "language" field with a unique name.
Each language service implementation is associated with the language for which it is
intended by means of this unique name.
<br/><br/>

Enter any user-readable text you like in the "description" field.
<br/><br/>

Enter a comma-separated list of file-name extensions in the "extensions" field
(do not include dots).
A file whose name has any of these extensions will be assumed to contain source code in the
new programming language, and the language services defined for this language will
become available to the developer while editing such files.
<br/><br/>

Hit "Finish" when done editing the various fields.
<br/><br/>

A SAFARI language description extension will be created using the above information.
</description>
</item>



<item title="Create a grammar and lexer specification">
<action pluginId="org.eclipse.imp.cheatsheets"
        class="org.eclipse.imp.cheatsheets.actions.NewParserAction"/>
<description>
Invoke "File" -&gt; "New" -&gt; "IDE Language Support" -&gt; "Parser Services" -&gt;
"JikesPG Grammar and Parser for UIDE".
<br/><br/>

Be sure that the proper names are entered into the project and language fields.
As these values are entered, reasonable default values will be entered into other fields.
<br/><br/>

If you wish, edit the "id" field to specify a non-default extension ID for the
parsing service.
<br/><br/>

If you wish, edit the "name" field to specify a non-default name for the
parsing service. This parameter is not presently used, but is intended to be
the user-visible name for the parser.
<br/><br/>

If you wish, edit the "class" field to specify a non-default fully-qualified
name for the parse controller. This class is used to give access to the token
stream, AST, and so on, to the various higher-level language services.
<br/><br/>

Hit "Finish" when done editing.  The JikesPG grammar file for your language will be
open in the editor, and the structure of the file should appear in the "Outline"
view.  The grammar file will contain some generally useful elements and some example
entries for a simple expression language.  You will need to edit this file
as apprpriate for your language.  (To acquire JikesPG--otherwise known as lpg--see
http://sourceforge.net/projects/lpg.)
<br/><br/>

Note:  The generated parser classes will depend on lpg to compile, so
the lpg.jar file should be added to your language project's build path.
</description>
</item>


<item title="Create a token colorer">
<action pluginId="org.eclipse.imp.cheatsheets"
        class="org.eclipse.imp.cheatsheets.actions.NewTokenColorerAction"/>
<description>
Invoke "File" -&gt; "New" -&gt; "IDE Language Support" -&gt; "Editor Services" -&gt;
"Token Colorer".
<br/><br/>

As before, assure that the names of your project and language have been entered
into the appropriate fields.
If desired, edit the remaining fields. Hit "Finish" when done.
<br/><br/>

You should see that the editor opens up the token colorer implementation.
The token colorer class has two important methods: the constructor, in which
a set of TextAttribute's are created (which are later used to specify the
text presentation for the various token kinds), and the getColoring() method,
which returns the TextAttribute to be used for the given token.
<br/><br/>

As you can see, getColoring() calls IToken.getKind() to determine the token
kind (represented by an integer), and uses that to compute the correct text
attributes. The set of valid token kinds is defined by the lexical analyzer;
they are typically located in the generated "Parsersym" interface (in the parser package),
and generally start with a prefix like "TK_".
</description>
</item>

<item title="Create an outliner">
<action pluginId="org.eclipse.imp.cheatsheets"
        class="org.eclipse.imp.cheatsheets.actions.NewOutlinerAction"/>
<description>
Invoke "File" -&gt; "New" -&gt; "IDE Language Support" -&gt; "Editor Services" -&gt;
"Outliner".
<br/><br/>

As before, enter the names of your project and language into the corresponding fields
and, if desired, edit the remaining fields. Hit "Finish" when done.
<br/><br/>

The outliner implementation should open in the editor.
The Outliner class only has one important method: the createOutlinePresentation(),
which typically retrieves the current AST from the IParseController and visits
it to populate the outline tree with various TreeItems.
Some example visit methods for the simple expression language are shown in the
generated class.
<br/><br/>

To add a program entity to the outline, simply override the visit method corresponding
to that type of AST node and have the overriding mehtod call createSubItem() with an appropriate label.
(The AbstractVisitor class contains default visit methods for all node types in
the AST.  This class may be located in a separate AST package or--depending on
parser-generator options--contained as a member class within the generated parser.)
</description>
</item>


<item title="Enable source-text folding">
<action pluginId="org.eclipse.imp.cheatsheets"
        class="org.eclipse.imp.cheatsheets.actions.NewFoldingUpdaterAction"/>
<description>
Invoke "File" -&gt; "New" -&gt; "IDE Language Support" -&gt; "Editor Services" -&gt;
"Source folding updater".
<br/><br/>

As before, be sure that the name of your language project is correctly filled in.
Additional fields will be filled in with default values on this basis.  If desired,
edit any of these fields.  Hit "Finish" when done.
<br/><br/>

The FoldingUpdater implementation should open in the editor.  Folding is achieved
by associating ProjectionAnnotations with regions of source text that are to be foldable.
The default implementation given here uses a visitor to walk the AST for the source
document; visit methods for various node types are presumed to create the annotations.
No visit methods are automatically generated; you will need to define a visit
method for each node type for which the source text is to be foldable.
<br/><br/>

The basic implementation of these visit methods is simple.  It is only necessary to call
the provided method makeAnnotation(..) and then return true or false depending
on whether children of the given node are to be visited.
(An example in the generated class shows this for a presumed AST node type that
represents blocks.)
The method makeAnnotation(..) assumes that the given node type is one that has been
generated by JikesPG.  If your AST node types have been created in some other way
then it may be necessary for you to revise the implementation of makeAnnotation(..).
<br/><br/>

You will also need to devise your own implementations of visit(..) or makeAnnotation(..)
if you want regions of foldable text that do not correspond exactly to the extent of an
AST node.
</description>
</item>


<item title="Enable hyperlink detection">
<action pluginId="org.eclipse.imp.cheatsheets"
        class="org.eclipse.imp.cheatsheets.actions.NewReferenceResolverAction"/>
<description>
Invoke "File" -&gt; "New" -&gt; "IDE Language Support" -&gt; "Editor Services" -&gt;
"Hyperlink Detector".
<br/><br/>

As before, be sure that the name of your language project is correctly filled in.
Additional fields will be filled in with default values on this basis.  If desired,
edit any of these fields.  Hit "Finish" when done.
<br/><br/>

The main class that implements the language-specific behavior for hyperlink
detection is the "reference resolver", and should come up in the editor.
For any AST node representing a program entity reference, the reference resolver
produces the AST node defining the entity to which it refers. In general, to
handle cross-compilation unit references, the AST node representing an entity
definition will have to identify both the owning compilation unit and the entity
within that compilation unit. The design of such a data structure is quite language-
specific, and is outside the scope of this tutorial.
<br/><br/>

Your language-specific reference resolver extends a language-indepedent abstract
class that provides basic implementations for most of the functions needed by
the hyperlink detector.  There are two main functions that need to be implemented
by your language-specific reference resolver.  One is getLinkTarget(Object, IParseController),
which finds the target node for a given source node.  The other is getLinkText(Object),
which gets the text to be associated with a link from a given node.  If this information
has already been computed, e.g., by a compiler for your language, then these methods may
simply need to retrieve it.  If the information has not been previously computed,
then these methods may have to perform some fairly complex calculations.
<br/><br/>

There are additional opportunities for customization of reference resolution related
to predetermination or filtering of types that may serve as the sources for hyperlinks.
Additional comments about these are found in the classes involved.
</description>
</item>


<item title="Create a builder">
<action pluginId="org.eclipse.imp.cheatsheets"
        class="org.eclipse.imp.cheatsheets.actions.NewBuilderAction"/>
<description>
Invoke "File" -&gt; "New" -&gt; "IDE Language Support" -&gt; "Core Services" -&gt;
"Incremental Builder".
<br/><br/>

As before, assure that the names of your project and language are entered in
the proper fields and, if desired, edit the remaining fields. Hit "Finish" when done.
<br/><br/>

Although it is not necessary to define a nature to which your builder will be
associated, this is a fairly common practice.  If the values for "hasNature" and
"isConfigurable" are left blank then they are treated as if false.
<br/><br/>

Although the parameter "name" and "value" fields are required here, they need to be
given meaningful values only if your builder will make use of external information
(which is not necessary for many builders).<br/><br/>

The IncrementalProjectBuilder implementation should open up in the editor.
<br/><br/>

The skeleton builder overrides or implements several methods (defined in its abstract
parent class SAFARIBuilderBase):<br/><br/>
 - getErrorMarker()<br/>
 - getInfoMarker()<br/>
 - getWarningMarker()<br/>
 - getPlugin()<br/>
 - isSourceFile()<br/>
 - isOutputFolder()<br/>
 - compile()<br/><br/>

Many of these will do reasonable things "out of the box". You will undoubtedly need to
edit compile() to actually call out to your compiler in some fashion, retrieve the
diagnostic messages and turn them into markers in the "Problems" view. If your
compiler runs in an external process, or uses java.io to create output files, you'll
also need to call IResource.refresh() on the folder that contains all the generated
output files (assuming that it is somewhere in your workspace).
<br/><br/>

Note:  You may need to define an implementation of IMessageHandler, so that the builder
can provide a message handler to the compiler, which the compiler can then use to call
back to the builder to report error messages.
</description>
</item>


<item title="To use your new language ...">
<description>
To use your new language and SAFARI IDE in a development project, you will need to
add a corresponding builder entry to the project's ".project" file.
If you have defined a nature for your language, you may also want to add a nature
entry to the project's ".project" file.
</description>
</item>


</cheatsheet>
