<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet title="Creating a Preference Service and Page for a new SAFARI IDE">
<intro>
<description>
SAFARI provides a preference service that is based on the Eclipse Preferences Service
(org.eclipse.core.internal.preferences.PreferencesService, since 3.0).
The SAFARI model of preferences is basically that of the Preferences Service.
This is a layered model, with four intrinsicly supported layers.
From most general to most specific, these are:<br/>
   1. Default<br/>
   2. Configuration (i.e., workspace configuration)<br/>
   3. Instance (i.e., workspace instance)<br/>
   4. Project<br/>
Preferences set at a given level are scoped accordingly, values set at lower levels override values set at higher levels,
with default values applying anywhere that a more specific value is lacking.
<br/><br/>

SAFARI initially supports a a style of preference page with four tabs, one for each of the four preference levels.
The page and the four tabs (with certain annotations and controls) are generated automatically by the SAFARI New Preference Page wizard.
As an alternative, SAFARI also supports the generation of a simple, untabbed preference page.
<br/><br/>

This step can be performed at any time after the language is described.
In particular, this step can be performed before any other step in which the
implementation might make use of the preferences service.
<br/><br/>


</description>
</intro>

<item title="Create a preference service and page">
<action pluginId="com.ibm.watson.safari.cheatsheets"
        class="com.ibm.watson.safari.cheatsheets.actions.NewPreferenceServiceAndPagesAction"/>
<description>

To invoke the New Preference Page wizard, select<br/><br/>
"File" -> "New" -> "IDE Language Support" -> "Core Services" -> "Preference Page"
<br/><br/>

In the wizard:<br/><br/>
    * As usual, assure that the names of the project and language are entered correctly.<br/><br/>
    * As a language may have multiple preference pages, you must specify a unique Eclispe identifier
    and usre-friendly name for a particular page<br/><br/>
    * As usual, edit the package and class name for the implementation to be what you want<br/><br/>
    * The optional "category" field is used to designate an existing preference page,
    if any, under which the new page will be listed in the Eclipse preferences menu (Window -> Preferences ...).
    To designate the "parent" page, you must provide its Eclipse id.<br/><br/>
    * Finally, if you do not wish to generate a full SAFARI preference page, you can generate a simple (untabbed)
    page with some text by filling that text into the "alternative" field.
    (If this field is left empty, then the usual tabbed SAFARI preference page will be generated).<br/><br/>
    * Hit "Finish" when done.<br/><br/>
The SAFARI preference pages are generated without any preference fields (or without any that are likely to be relevant to your language).
Fields for specific preferences must be added to complete the implementation of a preference page.
<br/><br/>

Additional information about the SAFARI preferences model and service, and about implementing SAFARI preference pages and fields,
can be found in "Preferences in SAFARI IDEs" (http://www.research.ibm.com/safari, and then navigate through the Documentation link).	

</description>
</item>


</cheatsheet>
