<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet title="Creating a Reference Resolver and Hyperlinking Service for a new SAFARI IDE">
<intro>
<description>
The goal of this step is to create an implementation for a reference resolution service.
This service is not apparent to users, but it enables a user-visible hyperlinking service
(that is implemented by a SAFARI library class and is automatically available once reference reslution
is supported), and it contributes to the implementation of a user-visible content-assist service.
<br/><br/>

This step must be performed after the grammar and parsing service have been defined.
It can be performed in any order with respect to the generation of many of the other IDE services
(such as token coloring, outlining, and folding), but it must be performed before the generation
of other services that depend on reference resolution (such as content assist).
<br/><br/>

</description>
</intro>

<item title="Create a reference resolver">
<action pluginId="com.ibm.watson.safari.cheatsheets"
        class="com.ibm.watson.safari.cheatsheets.actions.NewReferenceResolverAction"/>
<description>
The SAFARI wizard to generate the reference resolver is called "NewReferenceResolver" and is run by invoking<br/><br/>

"File" -> "New" -> "IDE Language Support" -> "Editor Services" -> "Reference Resolver"<br/><br/>

As with similar wizards, when you run this one, be sure that the name of the project and language are correct,
and edit the name of the implementation package and class as needed.  Hit "Finish" when done.
<br/><br/>

The wizard by default generates a referenceReslovers package with a ReferenceResolver class.
The principal methods to be implemented are getLinkTarget(node) and getLinkText(node).
The user can also implement methods that will perform filtering on given link source nodes to eliminate nodes
that aren't appropriate in that role.
<br/><br/>

Example implementations are provided in the generated class that work with the simple expression language
used for examples in the other services.
For getLinkTarget(..), the basic logic is to return null for any given node that cannot be a link source,
and for a node that can serve as a link sorce, to build a structure of the scopes and declarations of the
program (using an AST visitor), then to return the declaration of the given source as found in that structure.
Of course, in general, the details of reference resolution are langauge specific, and the amount of programming
required to complete the ReferenceResolver may depend on the functionality provided by avaliable language tools such as a compiler.
If available language tools already support reference resolution, then the ReferenceResolver may just need to retrieve
the relevant information from these tools.
On the other hand, if the available language tools do not support reference resolution, then the ReferenceResolver
may need to encode the logic necessary to perform resolution.
<br/><br/>

Once reference resolution is implemented, hyperlinking is automatically enabled in the language editor.
The hyperlinking service is implemented by a SAFARI library class and only depends on the ReferenceResolver to become functional.
Hyperlinking in a SAFARI editor works as it does in an Eclipse JDT Java editor, by control-clicking on a suitable link target.
<br/><br/>

Note:  The as with the NewFoldingUpdater wizard, the NewRererenceResolver wizard needs the name of the package that contains
AST node types.  If the value provided by default is not valid, then the class should be edited to fill in the correct name. 
<br/><br/>

</description>
</item>


</cheatsheet>
